<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief apologie for all non-subscribers, and looking-glasse for all apostate perjured prescribers &amp; subscribers of the new engagement, wherein they may clearly behold their presidents, sin, horrour, punishment.</title>
            <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E593_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872365</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165541</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165541)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 91:E593[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief apologie for all non-subscribers, and looking-glasse for all apostate perjured prescribers &amp; subscribers of the new engagement, wherein they may clearly behold their presidents, sin, horrour, punishment.</title>
                  <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Prynne.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "ffebr. 18."; the '50' in imprint date has been altered to "49".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York. .</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Loyalty oaths --  Great Britain --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Judgment of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165541:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF APOLOGIE For all <hi>NON-S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BSCRIBERS,</hi> AND LOOKING-GLASSE FOR ALL <hi>Apoſtate perjured Preſcribers</hi> &amp; <hi>Subſcribers</hi> OF THE New Engagement, Wherein they may clearly behold their <hi>Preſidents, Sin, Horrour, Puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:165541:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165541:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>BRIEF APOLOGIE</hi> For all NON-SUBSRIBERS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>HE that being often reproved, hardneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy,</hi> Prov. 29.11. How often the <hi>Preſcribers</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers</hi> of the <hi>New Engagement,</hi> againſt their manifold <hi>former Oaths, Vows, Proteſtations, Covenants</hi> and <hi>Engagements</hi> to the contrary, have been admoniſhed both in <hi>Preſs</hi> and <hi>Pulpit</hi> of the <hi>impiety, danger</hi> and <hi>deſtructive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of this their <hi>Apostacie</hi> and <hi>Perfidiouſneſs</hi> both to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> without any fruits of <hi>Reformation</hi> or <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> of this their <hi>execrable wickedneſs,</hi> is well known to their own <hi>ſelf-condemning conſciences</hi> and the <hi>world:</hi> Let them therefore now in this ſmall <hi>Looking-glaſs,</hi> behold both their <hi>Preſidents, Sin, Horrour of conſcience</hi> and their <hi>Puniſhments</hi> for the ſame, which if duely pondered, may through Gods mercy bring them to <hi>ſincere Repentance,</hi> or elſe create a <hi>tormenting hell</hi> within their <hi>Conſciences</hi> here, and plunge them into <hi>everlasting Hell-tormentings</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to their juſt deſtruction, who would receive no <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition</hi> in due ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Preſidents</hi> they follow in <hi>Preſcribing</hi> and <hi>Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing</hi> this <hi>Oath and Engagement,</hi> and very fatal and danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, even the very worſt of our <hi>Engliſh Rebels</hi> and <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> in former Ages.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo. Stow</hi> his Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of <hi>London,</hi> p. 88, 89, &amp;c. <hi>Hollinſhed, Speed</hi> &amp; <hi>Stow</hi> in 4 and 5 of R. 2.</note> In the fourth yeer of King <hi>Richard
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165541:3"/>the ſecond, Walter Tyler, Jack Straw,</hi> and their <hi>rebellious rout</hi> of the <hi>Peaſantry,</hi> made a great <hi>Inſurrection</hi> and <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> againſt the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Counſel;</hi> and marching up to <hi>London</hi> in a numerous body, by the favour of the meaner ſort of <hi>Citizens,</hi> who confederated with them, entred both the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Tower,</hi> beheaded the <hi>Archbiſhop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> with divers others, <hi>affronted, commanded</hi> and <hi>inſulted</hi> over the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Nobles</hi> at their pleaſures, as the onely <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England; tendring the King very high and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Propoſitions to ſigne,</hi> and notwithſtanding his <hi>preſent condeſcention to them,</hi> conſpired to ſeize upon <hi>his Perſon, and keep him alive amongst them for a time, that people might the more boldly repair to them, and think whatever they did was done by the Kings authority, till they had gotten power enough, that they needed not to fear any force which ſhould be made againſt them;</hi> And then they <hi>reſolved to ſtay all the Nobles that might give any counſel, or make any reſiſtance againſt them, together with all Lawyers, with the Knights of S.</hi> Johns <hi>and the</hi> Rhodes: And laſtly, they <hi>would have killed the King himſelf, with all men of poſſeſſions, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Canons, Parſons of Churches, and Monks,</hi> except Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>Mendicants;</hi> and have <hi>burnt and plundered the City of London it ſelf,</hi> and then have created <hi>Wat Tyler King</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and others of the <hi>Chief leading Rebels Kings in other Counties.</hi> And to engage all men in this Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie with them, they tendered an Oath to them, (ſomewhat better then this New <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement</hi>) viz. <hi>That they ſhould keep Allegeance to King</hi> Richard <hi>and</hi> TO THE COMMONS, <hi>and that they ſhould accept of no King that was named</hi> John; <hi>and that they ſhould be ready to aſſiſt them whenever they were called; and that they ſhould agree to no Tax to be levied or granted in the Kingdom, except a Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen. Which Oath they enforced all they met to take; and thoſe that were not ſworn to them, they took off both their Hoods and Heads.</hi> But after they had thus played <hi>Rex.</hi> and Lorded it over <hi>King, Nobles, Gentry, Country and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> a little ſpace, <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> their new <hi>King</hi> and <hi>General</hi> (who made this vaunt, <hi>that before four days came to an end,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165541:3"/>all the Laws of England ſhould proceed from his mouth</hi>) was ſtruck off his horſe by <hi>William Walworth</hi> Lord Maior of <hi>London,</hi> and ſlain in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> in the view of his <hi>Commons,</hi> and his head ſet upon <hi>London-bridge;</hi> and by the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Lord Maior, and about a thouſand loyal Citizens, in whoſe hearts the Law of the King was ingrafted, the King was reſcued f om their power and butchery, and the Rebels ſubdued, who threw down their weapons, fell to the ground and craved pardon; their principal Leaders and deſigned Kings taken and executed in all places, and their heads and parts hanged up for monuments to deter others; their confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates all diſperſed, impriſoned, and put to great fines and ranſoms to redeem their lives and liberties.</hi> And ſo their new <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Republike</hi> quickly ended in a fatal <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie.</hi> The <hi>King,</hi> for the Lord <hi>Maiors and Citizens good ſervice,</hi> in perpetual memory of all of this their Loyalty, <hi>Knighted the Maior,</hi> and added the <hi>Dagger</hi> to the <hi>Cities Arms;</hi> which the preſent Lord Maior, Aldermen and packed Common-Councel-men may do well to conſider, for fear they alter the <hi>Dagger</hi> into an <hi>Ax</hi> or <hi>Halter</hi> for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and the <hi>Preſcribers</hi> of this new <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (who tread in theſe rebellious Traytors ſteps, and proſecute their very deſignes and Engagement) may do well in time to remember their ſad Story, leſt they arrive at their fatal ends, to their temporal and eternal ruine. The like deſigne and project in effect was afterwards hatched and ſet on foot by <hi>Jack Cade</hi> and his <hi>rebellious rout,</hi> under pretence to <hi>reform Laws</hi> and <hi>Government;</hi> who were all ſcattered, came to the like <hi>Tragical ends,</hi> and for ever branded by an Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. c. 1. for wicked <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traitors</hi> to poſterity.</p>
            <p>In the Month<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Acts and Monum. 1640. Vol. 2. p. 665. to 677.</note> of <hi>July,</hi> 1549, in the third yeer of King <hi>Edward the ſixth,</hi> as the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>Devonſhire</hi> and <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal</hi> raiſed an <hi>Inſurrection</hi> againſt the <hi>King and his Councel</hi> in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> ſo the <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire</hi> at the ſame time raiſed a <hi>Rebellion</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> principally out of <hi>their traiterous hearts, grudging at the Kings honourable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in reforming Religion; and truſting to a blinde
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165541:4"/>Prophecy wherewith they were ſeduced, which themſelves thought ſhould ſhortly come to paſs, by reaſon of the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions then on foot in</hi> Norfolk <hi>and</hi> Devonſhire; <hi>the tenour of Prophecie, and purpoſe of which Traytors together, was,</hi> THAT THERE SHOULD NO KING RAIGN IN ENGLAND;<note place="margin">Nota.</note> THAT THE NOBLEMEN AND GEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TLEMEN SHOULD BE DESTROYED, AND THE REALM SHOULD BE RULED BY FOUR GOVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOURS TO BE ELECTED and APPOINTED BY THE COMMONS HOLDING A PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT IN COMMOTION, (without <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Lords</hi>) <hi>to begin at the South and North Seas of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereupon, to execute this their deſigne, and erect this their new <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> without <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> (the very project now on foot, and ſcope of this new <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Engagement</hi>) they reſolved to ſeize and <hi>murther ſuch Nobles</hi> and Gentlemen of Eſtate in their Houſes and Counties, and in executing the Kings Commiſſions, as were favourers of the Kings proceedings, and likely to reſiſt them. Hereupon, the King ſent his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pardon and perſwaſions to them, to reduce them by all fair means to obedience; informing them, <hi>that He was their rightful King, Liege Lord and Soveraign King of England, not by age, but</hi> BY GODS ORDINANCE, BEING ORDAINED THEIR KING AND PRINCE BY ALMIGHTY GOD, poſſeſſing his Crown BY BLOOD AND DESCENT FROM HIS ROYAL FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER KING <hi>HENRY</hi> THE EIGHTH. <hi>You are Our Subjects, becauſe We be your King; and rule we will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath willed. It is as great a fault in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, not to rule, as in a Subject not to obey. If it be conſidered, they which move this matter</hi> (of his Non-age) <hi>if they durſt utter themſelves, would deny Our Kingdom. But Our good Subjects know their Prince, and will increaſe, not diminiſh his Honour; enlarge, not abate his Power; knowledge, not defer his Kingdom to certain yeers: all is one, to ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Crown, and to deny our Kingdom, as to require that our Laws may be broken until one and twenty yeers,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165541:4"/>
               <hi>Dare then any of you, with the name of a Subject, ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Act of Parliament, a Law of the Whole Realm? What is Our Power, if Laws ſhould be thus neglected? Yea,</hi> WHAT IS YOUR SURETY, IF LAWS BE NOT KEPT? <hi>Herein indeed reſteth Our Honour, herein ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our Kingdom, herein do all Kings knowledge us a King: And ſhall any of you dare breathe or think againſt our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, our Kingdom or Crown?</hi> &amp;c. But neither the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don nor Reaſon prevailing, theſe obſtinate Rebels were at laſt twice or thrice vanquiſhed and utterly routed by a ſmall number of the Kings Forces, <hi>many thouſands of them ſlain,</hi> others <hi>taken priſoners</hi> and <hi>executed,</hi> and the <hi>reſt ſcattered, ſo that they could never make head again,</hi> by the avenging hand and juſt judgement of God. And ſo their expected new <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian Republicke</hi> and <hi>Parliament of Commons,</hi> without <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> came ſoon to ruine, before it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any eſtabliſhment. Let our New Moulders of our Engliſh <hi>Republike,</hi> and promoters of the New <hi>Engagement,</hi> to ſet up a <hi>Republike</hi> and <hi>Parliament without King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> for the future, conſider this ill ſucceſs of this deſigne heretofore with fear and trembling, leſt it prove their very caſe in concluſion.</p>
            <p>King,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Acts &amp; Monum. Vol. 3. p. 13, 14, 15, 16, &amp;c. <hi>Hollinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, Speed</hi> &amp; <hi>Stow,</hi> in 1 <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Edward the ſixth</hi> lying on his death-bed, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his Siſter <hi>Queen Mary</hi> to be an <hi>obſtinate Papiſt,</hi> like to ſubvert that Religion and Reformation which he had eſtabliſhed, did by advice of his <hi>Councel,</hi> and <hi>learned Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers,</hi> by his <hi>laſt Will and Teſtament,</hi> endeavour to diſinherit her of the Crown, appointing the Lady <hi>Jane</hi> to ſucceed him: and to eſtabliſh <hi>her Title</hi> thereto, cauſed <hi>all his Privie Councel, moſt of the chief Nobility, the Maior and City of</hi> London, <hi>and all the Judges</hi> (exept Judge <hi>Hales</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> who refuſed the ſubſcription, and <hi>chief Lawyers of the Realm</hi>) <hi>to ſubſcribe thereto,</hi> againſt the expreſs <hi>Statute</hi> of 35 <hi>H.</hi> 8 c. 1. (to which they and the whole Kingdom had ſworn) taking the <hi>Oath</hi> for <hi>the ſucceſſion of the Crown therein preſcribed.</hi> Hereupon, after King <hi>Edwards</hi> deceaſe, they all proclaimed <hi>Jane Queen,</hi> and rejected <hi>Mary,</hi> againſt whom they ſent the <hi>Duke of Northumberland</hi> with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165541:5"/>who departing from <hi>London,</hi> the Lords of the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel perceiving the generality of the people to adhere to Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>and that ſhe began to gather a conſiderable ſtrength, and moſt of the common people, and ſome of the Lords ſtanding for her,</hi> thereupon <hi>they preſently turned their ſong, proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Mary <hi>eldeſt daughter to King</hi> Henry, <hi>Queen,</hi> according to the Act of Parliament, and deſerted <hi>Jane,</hi> to whoſe Title they had <hi>ſubſcribed:</hi> whereupon the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> the <hi>Duke of Suffolk,</hi> Sir <hi>John Gates,</hi> (three <hi>of the Subſcribers</hi>) together with the Lord <hi>Gilford, Lord Gray,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Wyat,</hi> and ſundry others were ſuddenly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, <hi>condemned and executed as Traytors,</hi> together with the new <hi>Queen Jane;</hi> who all confeſſed their <hi>deaths and condemnation to be juſt,</hi> and that they <hi>deſerved to die for theſe their Treaſons; wiſhing all others to beware by their examples, and timely to ſubmit to and obey Queen</hi> Mary <hi>without murmuring or rebelling againſt her, as good Subjects ought to do.</hi> This was the Tragick end of thoſe <hi>Subſcribers</hi> and <hi>Engagers</hi> to diſinherite this <hi>Queen</hi> of her Birthright, and ſet up another againſt the Law, and their <hi>Oathes of Allegeance.</hi> Which our preſent <hi>Subſcribers</hi> and <hi>Engagers</hi> may do well to ruminate upon, their caſe being far worſe and more treaſonable againſt the <hi>King,</hi> then theirs againſt <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> having King <hi>Edwards</hi> laſt Will, with all the Kings Councel, moſt Nobles, Judges, Lawyers, and the Citizens of <hi>Londons</hi> Subſcriptions thereto in King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> life-time, to countenance them herein; all which theſe recant, againſt his clear Title by the Statute of 1 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 1, 2.</p>
            <p>But theſe Examples perchance may extend onely to ſuch who have been, or hereafter ſhall appear in Arms againſt the preſent <hi>King,</hi> to diſinherit him of his Crown and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; or to the chief <hi>Contrivers</hi> and <hi>Promoters</hi> of the <hi>New Engagement.</hi> I ſhall therefore remember all meer <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers</hi> of it, through baſe fear, cowardice, covetouſneſs, or other unworthy ends, againſt their former <hi>Oathes of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, Allegeance, Judges, Juſtices, Sheriffs, Officers, Clerks,</hi> and the like, their <hi>Proteſtation, Vow, and Solemn
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165541:5"/>League and Covenant,</hi> of three memorable Examples of bare <hi>Subſcribers</hi> onely againſt their <hi>Judgements</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> meerly <hi>to ſave their lives, when in moſt certain and apparent danger;</hi> the conſideration whereof may make their ſouls and joynts to quake and tremble, and put them into <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> trembling agony.</p>
            <p>The firſt is that of M.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Acts and Monum. Vol. 2. p. 265, 271, 272 <hi>Latimers</hi> 7 and 8 Sermons</note> 
               <hi>Tho. Bilney,</hi> a pious and famous Martyr in <hi>King Henry</hi> the 8 's Raign; who being condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for <hi>Hereſie</hi> by ſome <hi>Popiſh Prelates,</hi> was <hi>induced to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure, and ſubſcribe his hand to a renounciation of thoſe Truths of God which he formerly profeſſed, and for maintenance whereof he was condemned to be burnt.</hi> But no ſooner was he releaſed, <hi>but he was ſo extremely troubled and tormented in conſcience for neer two yeers ſpace after, that his friends were afraid to let him be alone by himſelf, and fain to be with him day and night, to comfort him as they could; but no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort would ſerve. As for the comfortable places of Scripture, to bring them unto him, it was as though a man ſhould run him thorow the heart with a ſword. He was in ſuch an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, that nothing did him good, neither eating nor drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor any other communication of Gods Word; for he thought that all the whole Scriptures were againſt him, and ſounded to his condemnation. At laſt by Gods grace, and good counſel, coming to ſome quietneſs of conſcience, he fully reſolved to give over his life for the confeſſion of that Faith which he had formerly abjured and ſubſcribed againſt:</hi> and thereupon preaching and maintaining it publikely, was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, burnt, and undauntedly ſealed it with his blood, to make amends for his former cowardly and unworthy <hi>ſubſcription,</hi> having no peace of conſcience till then.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is that of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Acts &amp; Monum. Vol. 2. p. 297, 299, 300 301.</note> 
               <hi>James Bainham</hi> a <hi>Lawyer</hi> of the middle <hi>Temple,</hi> who being <hi>impriſoned, perſecuted, whipped, ſtocked, chained, wracked, and cruelly tormented</hi> by Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Moor,</hi> then Lord Chancellour, for his profeſſion of Religion, and ready to be condemned and burnt for an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick,</hi> was at laſt, after many denials, for <hi>fear of death, and to preſerve his life, perſwaded to abjure the articles and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions charged againſt him, and ſubſcribe to their abjuration
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165541:6"/>under his hand.</hi> And having done his Penance, was ſet at liberty. But <hi>within one month after, he exceedingly bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this his ſubſcription and abjuration, and was never quiet in his minde and conſcience, until he had uttered his fall to all his acquaintance, and asked God and the world for giveneſs before all the Congregation,</hi> (in thoſe days in Bowe-lane:) <hi>And immediately the next Sunday after, he came to S.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins <hi>Church with the New Teſtament in his hand in Engliſh, and The obedience of a Chriſtian man, in his boſom, and ſtood up there before the people in his Pew, there declaring openly with weeping tears, that he had denied God; and prayed all the people to forgive him, and to beware of his weakneſs, and not to do as he did; for (ſaid he) if I ſhould not return again to the Truth</hi> (having the New Teſtament in his hand) <hi>this Word of God would damn me both body and ſoul at the day of Judgement. And then he prayed every body rather to die by and by, then to do as he did:</hi> FOR HE WOULD NOT FEEL SUCH AN HELL AGAIN AS HE DID FEEL, FOR ALL THE WORLDS GOOD. After which he had no quiet, till he writ likewiſe certain Letters to the Biſhop his brother, and others, to juſtifie the Truths he had renounced under his hands, and ſuffered for them at the Stake, to which he was ſoon after condemned: where being in the midſt of the flames round about him, and <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his legs and arms half burnt and conſumed,</hi> he ſpake thus with a loud voice: <hi>O ye Papiſts, behold, ye look for Miracles, and here now ye may ſee a Miracle: for in this fire I feel no more pain, then if I were in a bed of down; but it is to me as a bed of roſes.</hi> So that he who felt ſuch an horrour and hell in conſcience before, for ſubſcribing againſt the Truth and his Conſcience even whiles he was at large, felt no pain nor torment at all in his body in the midſt of the flames, when chained to the Stake, and half burnt to aſhes, and had then a very heaven in his Soul and Conſcience. An admirable preſident both of Gods juſtice towards coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Subſcribers, and comfortable aſſiſtance of conſtant Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Adherers to the Truth, and their primitive Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:165541:6"/>
The third is the memorable example of<note n="*" place="margin">Fox Acts &amp; Monum. Vol.3. p.666 to 677.</note> 
               <hi>Archbiſhop Cranmer,</hi> who ſubſcribed to <hi>Queen Maries diſinheriting, againſt his Oath firſt; and after that, being condemned to be burnt for an Heretick, upon the ſollicitation of ſome Friers and others, who aſſured him, that if he recanted his former Tenents againſt the Papiſts, he ſhould not onely ſave his life, of which elſe there was no hopes, but likewiſe be reſtored to the Queens favour and his former honours, was induced to ſubſcribe ſuch a Recantation as they tendered him, (to the great ſcandal of Religion, and triumph of the Papiſts) and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, to write and ſubſcribe two Copies thereof, with his own hand.</hi> For which Subſcription, he was ſo <hi>grieved and tormented in Conſcience, that the image and ſhape of perfect ſorrow appeared in his countenance, and ſometimes he lifted up his hands to heaven for pardon, and ſometimes let them fall down to earth for ſhame and anguiſh; the tears in the mean time guſhing out from his eyes ſo abundantly, trickling down his aged cheeks, that men never ſaw ſo many tears in any childe, as burſt out in him, which moved all mens hearts to commiſeration.</hi> When he came to ſpeak to the people, <hi>he exorted them, That next under God they ſhould obey their King and Queen willingly and gladly, without murmuring or grudging, not for fear of them onely, but much more for the fear of God; knowing that they be Gods Miniſters, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God to rule and govern them; and therefore Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever reſiſteth them, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God.</hi> Then he told them ſeveral times, <hi>that there was one Great thing and offence he had committed, which did moſt of all vex and trouble him at that time, and did trouble his conſcience much more then any thing he ever did or ſaid in all his life; and that was, his ſetting his hand to a writing contrary to the truth, which I (ſaid he) here now renounce and refuſe, as things written with my hand contrary to the truth, which I thought in mine heart, and written for fear of death, and to ſave my life, if it might be: and that is, all ſuch Bills and Papers which I have written or ſigned with my hand ſince my degradation. And foraſmuch as my hand offended, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting contrary to my heart, my hand ſhall firſt be puniſhed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165541:7"/>therefore, it ſhall be firſt burned. Whereupon, the fire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindled, and coming neer him, ſtretching forth his arm, he put his right hand into the flame; which he held ſo ſtedfaſt and immoveable therein, (ſave onely that he wiped his face therewith) that all men might ſee his hand quite burnt before his body was touched:</hi> taking this exemplary revenge and puniſhment upon it, for his ſcandalous Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</p>
            <p>Let every <hi>Miniſter, Lawyer,</hi> and other conſcientious <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> then, that hath any fear of God, or remainders of Conſcience left within him, which out of fear, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or any ſordid unchriſtian ends whatſoever, (when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his life nor liberty lay at ſtake, as theſe Martyrs did) hath perfidiouſly, traiterouſly, and unchriſtianly ſubſcribed this <hi>New Engagement</hi> and <hi>Oath,</hi> with the <hi>ſelf-ſame</hi> hand which he hath formerly <hi>lifted up to the moſt high God,</hi> in the <hi>Publike Congregation,</hi> or in the <hi>Parliament-Houſe,</hi> or <hi>open Court in Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall, when he took the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant;</hi> and wherewith he publikely <hi>ſubſcribed the ſame,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>ſwore</hi> the <hi>Oathes</hi> of <hi>Supremacie, Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, Fealty, Homage,</hi> or any other Oathes diametrically contrary to them, to wit, <hi>To bear Faith and true Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the King,</hi> HIS HEIRS AND SUCCESSORS, AND HIM AND THEM, WITH ALL THE ROY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ALTIES AND PRIVILEDGES ANNEXED OR UNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED TO THE IMPERIAL CROWN OF THIS REALM, &amp;c. TO ASSIST, MAINTAIN AND DEFEND WITH THEIR LIVES AND ESTATES, AGAINST ALL PERSONS WHATSOEVER; And to procure THEIR PROFIT, &amp;c. holding it all the time he ſwore upon the Bible or Evangeliſts; and <hi>to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of both Houſes of Parliament, and zealouſly and conſtantly to perſevere therein all the days of his life, and not to be withdrawn from the ſame by any perſwaſion, combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, fear or terrour whatſoever,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as they ſhould anſwer the contrary at the Great day of Judgement before the ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of all hearts,</hi> &amp;c. ſadly and ſeriouſly conſider of theſe doleful Examples, and with what face or conſcience he can
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165541:7"/>henceforth lift up his <hi>perjured hands</hi> to God in <hi>Prayer,</hi> or look any conſcientious <hi>Covenanter</hi> in the face, till he hath with horrour of conſcience, and whole rivers of tears, ſighs and groans of ſpirit, and publike abjuration and recantation of this his <hi>Perjury, Treachery, weakneſs</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> and renounced, bewailed, and abjured this his New <hi>ungodly Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription:</hi> And then he will either imitate theſe eminent Martyrs in their horrours of conſcience, contrition, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, confeſſion and abjuration of this their Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuffering manfully (if there be occaſion) for their <hi>Oathes, Vows, Covenant, Proteſtation,</hi> and <hi>Engagements;</hi> or elſe fall into abſolute deſperation of any pardon or remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from God and man, and with <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Abithophel</hi> (two Arch-<hi>traitors</hi>) hang and execute themſelves, for this their <hi>abominable Treachery, Perjury to God, the King, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Kingdom.</hi> Which conſideration and Preſidents, may be a ſufficient <hi>Apologie</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> to juſtifie and excuſe all <hi>Non-ſubſcribers</hi> of this <hi>Engagement,</hi> againſt all imperious <hi>Preſcribers</hi> and <hi>Inforcers</hi> thereof, (eſpecially if pretenders to <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> in ſo eminent a degree, as the chief <hi>Contrivers</hi> thereof pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) and exempt them from all injurious <hi>Penalties, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures or Loſſes</hi> menaced for their <hi>Non-ſubſcription,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the <hi>Tribunals of heaven</hi> and <hi>earth;</hi> which cannot but give ſentence of <hi>abſolution</hi> in their behalf, ſince God himſelf expreſly and peremptorily commands them, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Ye ſhall not ſwear by my Name falſly, neither ſhalt thou prophane the Name of thy God: I am the LORD;</hi> and denounceth many ſevere <hi>Judgements</hi> againſt breakers of <hi>Oathes</hi> and <hi>Covenants</hi> thorowout the<note n="a" place="margin">Neh. 5.12, 13. Jer. 34.6. to 20. Ezek. 17.11. to 32. Zech. 5.1. to 5. Mal. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Old</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 1.29, 30, 31. 1 Tim. 1.10. 2 Tim. 3.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="corollary">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:165541:8"/>
               <head>A Corollary to the Premiſes.</head>
               <p>UNto all theſe ancient and moſt memorable Examples of Gods apparent diſpleaſure, and Conſciences fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful workings againſt all ungodly actings and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt lawful Authority, and former righteous and religious Vows, Oathes, and Covenants, might here moſt pertinently be added three or four more remarkable and moſt freſh Examples of Gods juſt indignation, and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences affrightings, fallen out very lately among us, in theſe our moſt diſloyal, apoſtarizing days, upon the perju ious ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſubſcribing to this preſent new <hi>Engagement:</hi> As namely, of a Scholar in <hi>Trinity</hi>-Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> a Miniſter in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and a Cirizen of <hi>Whitington</hi>-Colledge in <hi>London.</hi> But there is one more lately fallen out among us, which ſhall be <hi>inſtar multorum,</hi> in ſtead of many other, as coming up more clearly and cloſely to this our preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And, O that ſuch a ſad and ſorrowful ſtory had never been told in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor publiſhed in the ſtreets of <hi>Askalon!</hi> But Divine providence having ſo ordered, that it is ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely and notoriouſly known; we cannot but make this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like uſe of it, for juſt terrour and affrightment of all ſuch like offenders, whereof both City and Country at this time, too rankly abound among us. Now the ſad relation or ſtory is this. One M. <hi>Tho. Hoyle,</hi> late Lo. Maior of <hi>York,</hi> and one of the moſt unhappie Members of the Juncto of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who having been in all the former part of his life lookt upon and known to have been a moſt eminent profeſſor of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and of an unblameable life and converſation. But ſince his being a Member of the Houſe of Commons, having been made Maſter of Sir <hi>Peter Oſborns</hi> Office, a place of much credit and profit, and a Committee of the Kings Revenue, (fat morſels, to ſtifle and choak Conſcience) when the Houſe was purged by the power of the Army, this Gentleman abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill in the Houſe with the reſt of the Juncto, and acting
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165541:8"/>all along with them, was liſted in the number of thoſe that were to be Judges of the Kings life or death; but (as it is certainly reported) was not preſent at the Kings Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. But, afterward, when the Juncto enacted the taking, and themſelves alſo took this <hi>New Engagement,</hi> he not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſented in it, but (though againſt the dictate of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as he had often profeſſed to divers, upon ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions thereunto) himſelf alſo took it, and ſubſcribed to it: wherefore, after this thus taking of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> being (as it too apparently was manifeſted in him) greatly troubled in conſcience about it, he formerly (I mean, before this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fatal act was effected) had attempted to have deſtroyed himſelf; but failing thereof, upon the 30 of <hi>Jan.</hi> laſt, 1649. about the fore-part of that afternoon, being in his houſe at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and watching and obtaining an opportunity of being retired from all company, in his chamber, having provided a Cord in his pocket, he moſt wofully hanged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf therewith. Of which his moſt lamentable and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſelf-Murther, although divers do give various cenſures, eſpecially the Malignant or Royal party, principally becauſe he was liſted one of the Judges of the King, and this his woful ſelf-ruine fell out on the very ſame day twelvemonth, and neer upon the very time of that day whereon the King was put to death, (which I cannot but acknowledge was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable;) yet the firſt and ſafeſt uſe thereof which godly Chriſtians ought to make, may be Caution to every one of us, ſeriouſly to conſider what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Let him that thinks he ſtands, take heed leſt he fall.</hi> Secondly, let, O let thoſe moſt ungodly ſelf-ſeeking Preſcribers of this perjurious <hi>Engagement,</hi> look unto it, and be terrified by it, whom in a moſt ſpecial manner it moſt neerly concerns. Yea, in the third place, let all thoſe falfe-hearted, poſted, perjured Divines, which have ſo ſinfully ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed this <hi>Engagement,</hi> lay this lamentable example cloſe to their hearts; eſpecially thoſe two unworthy, low-ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet buſie Champions for the <hi>Engagement,</hi> (though, God be thanked, with very ill ſucceſs, both to the Scribler and Licenſer) M. <hi>John Dury,</hi> and M. <hi>Joſeph Caryl,</hi> who have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165541:9"/>ſo ſtrugled to bring others into the ſame condemnation with themſelves. And in the fourth and laſt place, let all Conſcience-muffled and perfidious Malignants or Royalliſts alſo lay this moſt woful example very cloſe to their ſouls and conſciences; who, notwithſtanding they moſt falſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend themſelves to be the loyalleſt and moſt loving Subjects to our late deceaſed King and his Poſterity, and ſuch faſt friends to Monarchy and Kingly Government; yet have moſt diſloyally and and perfidiouſly taken this <hi>Engagement,</hi> and that upon a moſt wicked and baſe Maxime of theirs, lately taken up among them, that, <hi>He is a fool that will not take it, and he is a knave that will not break it.</hi> Thus, like <hi>Atheiſts</hi> indeed, either believing there is no God to puniſh their perjury, or elſe that they have God at command, to repent when they pleaſe. But let them ſee and know, (as here by this moſt woful Example is moſt evident) how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely and wrathfully the Lord will, ſooner or later, be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on all Perjurers and Covenant-breakers: And, let them therefore, (as that even Prophetical Author of <hi>The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment of the Engagement,</hi> lately publiſhed, did religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adviſe all Preſcribers and Subſcribers of the <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in the cloſure of that his ſaid Treatiſe; a paſſage moſt remarkable, eſpecially conſidering this moſt ſad example; which fell out ſo immediately after it, and which therefore cannot be too often inculcated and repeated;) <hi>Let them all</hi> (I ſay) <hi>either, with Peter, after he had abjured his Lord and Maſter with an oath, go forth, preſently, and weep bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly; or elſe, with treacherous Judas, who betrayed his Lord and Maſter, to gratifie the High-prieſts, go forth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing, and hang themſelves, to avoid the ſhame of the world, and intolerable anguiſh of their tormanting Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <hi>Optimum eſt alienâ f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui inſaniâ.</hi>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
